<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DIPr Lab at PSU</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>DIPr Lab at PSU</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0f0a8221e05ad032f2ae11441278135b_1259_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>DIPr Lab at PSU</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Event</title>
      <link>/event/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further event details, including page elements such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CyberPDX 2024</title>
      <link>/post/07-29-24-cyberpdx/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/07-29-24-cyberpdx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About CyberPDX:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CyberPDX is a no-cost 5-day residential summer STEAM camp hosted at the Portland State University Maseeh College of Engineering &amp;amp; Computer Science. This year&amp;rsquo;s camp is designed for Native and Indigenous high school students to introduce them to cybersecurity skills, principles, policies, and careers through an interactive STEAM curriculum and career exposure. All are welcome. The camp activities will be led by many PSU faculty and local experts, which includes local Indigenous leaders. This is an incredible opportunity for Native and Indigenous students to get an immersive, interdisciplinary, and fun experience on a college campus. No prior experience is necessary, and beginners are welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year&amp;rsquo;s CyberPDX had threads on Cryptography, Programming, Privacy, Policy and Film. &lt;a href=&#34;/author/primal-pappachan/&#34;&gt;Primal Pappachan&lt;/a&gt; was the instructor for the Privacy thread and &lt;a href=&#34;/author/dylan-conklin/&#34;&gt;Dylan Conklin&lt;/a&gt; was the Teaching Assistant. The topics covered in this thread include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importance of Privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Difference between Privacy and Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debating risk versus convenience of app features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading Privacy Policies of Social Media Applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming in Python to use Generative AI as a Privacy Assistant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about, please check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pdx.edu/engineering/cyberpdx-cybersecurity-camp-native-indigenous-high-school-students&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CyberPDX website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RPE presentation - Anadi Shakya</title>
      <link>/post/06-21-24-anadi-rpe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/06-21-24-anadi-rpe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/author/anadi-shakya/&#34;&gt;Anadi Shakya&lt;/a&gt; successfully completed the oral part of her Research Profiency Examination (RPE) on &lt;strong&gt;‘Sieve and Cache: Scalable Access Control for Dynamic IoT Applications’&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Committee Members&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;/author/primal-pappachan/&#34;&gt;Primal Pappachan&lt;/a&gt; (Portland State University) ; Dave Maier (Portland State University) ; Wu-chang Feng (Portland State University)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The proliferation of smart technologies and newer privacy regulations necessitate effective management of user preferences about data sharing using access control policies. Current Database Management Systems (DBMS) struggle to efficiently answer queries while enforcing a large number of Fine-Grained Access Control (FGAC) policies. Sieve is a middleware for relational DBMSs that generate guarded expressions, which are efficient rewriting of queries with a given set of policies. In this paper, we extend Sieve with caching of guarded expressions to better handle dynamic workloads involving a series of policy insertions and queries at different frequencies. Our novel caching approach includes a replacement policy based on clock algorithm and a refresh strategy based on cost analysis to select between regeneration and update of guarded expressions. We also develop a workload generator that creates different workloads with different distributions of policies, and queries that are relevant to a chosen scenario. These workloads simulate realistic IoT scenarios, such as smart campus applications. Experimental results show that Sieve, enhanced with caching, is effective in terms of cache-hits and efficient in terms of system load and latency of query answering, in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIPr Lab at 2024 Summer Research Academy (SRA)</title>
      <link>/post/06-21-24-sra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/06-21-24-sra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summer Research Academy (SRA) is designed to engage undergraduate students interested in making a difference in
their communities by pursuing research opportunities in STEM, biomedical, behavioral, clinical, health, and social
sciences.  Students do not have to have prior research experience to participate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DIPr lab had a table at SRA 2024 with the following members attending (from left to right): &lt;a href=&#34;/author/nicholas-g.e.-morales/&#34;&gt;Nicholas G.E. Morales&lt;/a&gt;, Michael Howard, &lt;a href=&#34;/author/satvik-mudgal/&#34;&gt;Satvik Mudgal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/author/steve-willoughby/&#34;&gt;Steve Willoughby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/author/primal-pappachan/&#34;&gt;Primal Pappachan&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;/author/dylan-conklin/&#34;&gt;Dylan Conklin&lt;/a&gt;. We had many interested undergraduates stop by our table to learn about our various research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about, please check out their website &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/pdx.edu/2024-sra/home-page?authuser=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2024 SRA website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Securing IoT Communication Protocols at Scale</title>
      <link>/project/pubsubcontrol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pubsubcontrol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The world of the connected “Internet of Things” is expanding to include more devices which observe our daily lives, routines, locations, and even our state of health. But have the underlying protocols by which they communicate this data kept pace with the need to protect our privacy and security?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we will investigate various “middleware” approaches to injecting dynamic access control agents into existing MQTT broker servers and measure their performance on real and/or simulated network environments as well as their resilience to security threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek to strengthen the protocols underlying the communication between IoT devices, such as MQTT, to adjudicate who is authorized to access which information, where the access parameters may rapidly and frequently change, without impacting performance, based on the implications of the MQTT message topic hierarchical structure combined with geospacial security policy “zones” and techniques to simplfy and consolidate policy rules in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accord</title>
      <link>/project/accord/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/accord/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Users are increasingly adopting collaborative cloud services like Google Drive.
The lack of fine-grained access controls on many cloud services make actions that violate the expectations of other users likely, resulting in multiuser conflicts.
For example, a user with editor permissions may add a user outside the organization and revoke the permissions of another user, all without consent from the original resource owner.
These multiuser conflicts may compromise a resource&amp;rsquo;s confidentiality, integrity, or availability, leading to a lack of trust in cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ACCORD is a web application built on top of Google Drive which prevents and detects multiuser conflicts.
It employs a simulator to help users preemptively identify potential conflicts and
assist them in defining action constraints.
Then, using these action constraints, ACCORD can automatically detect future conflicts and suggest resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, we are testing the scalability and practicality of ACCORD with larger numbers of users and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blue Crab</title>
      <link>/project/bluecrab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/bluecrab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Blue Crab is a mobile app based on Flutter, which combines GPS with Bluetooth scanning to detect unwanted trackers. Its purpose is to experiment with alternative methods to prevent unwanted trackers by taking a proactive approach, allowing users to see a report about all the devices of concern around them&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sieve</title>
      <link>/project/sieve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/sieve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SIEVE is a versatile middleware that enhances access control in DBMS, enabling efficient query processing even with a large number of access control policies. We&amp;rsquo;re currently integrating caching to further improve query performance. Additionally, we&amp;rsquo;ve developed a workload generator that simulates various scenarios to test policy models and ensure access control compliance, reflecting real-world conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tattletale</title>
      <link>/project/tattletale/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/tattletale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tattletale uses denial constraints to discovery data inferences inside of a database relative to sensitive cells.  The cells that make up the denial constraints are then checked to see which cells infer information on them.  In the end all the cells that infer data on the sensitive cells and the cells that could be used to reconstruct those inferences are placed into a list which is used to generate a view that does not contain those cells.  Since inference can only be reconstructed as long as only one predicate is missing we can use that to minimize how many cells we have to hide.  The benefit of Tattletale is that it provides protection against inference which access control lists don&amp;rsquo;t provide.  The current challenge is trying to improve the run time performance and decrease the number of cells that have to be hidden while also guaranteeing a certain level of protection against reconstruction.Tattletale uses denial constraints to discovery data inferences inside of a database relative to sensitive cells.  The cells that make up the denial constraints are then checked to see which cells infer information on them.  In the end all the cells that infer data on the sensitive cells and the cells that could be used to reconstruct those inferences are placed into a list which is used to generate a view that does not contain those cells.  Since inference can only be reconstructed as long as only one predicate is missing we can use that to minimize how many cells we have to hide.  The benefit of Tattletale is that it provides protection against inference which access control lists don&amp;rsquo;t provide.  The current challenge is trying to improve the run time performance and decrease the number of cells that have to be hidden while also guaranteeing a certain level of protection against reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACCORD: Constraint-driven mediation of multi-user conflicts in cloud services</title>
      <link>/publication/accord/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/accord/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GenAIPABench: A Benchmark for Generative AI-based Privacy Assistants</title>
      <link>/publication/genaipa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/genaipa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to DIPr lab at PSU</title>
      <link>/post/21-01-24-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/21-01-24-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Data &amp;amp; Internet Privacy Lab offically starts at the Portland State University. We are a diverse group of researchers studying problems in user privacy, data management, access control, differential privacy, systems, algorithms, and privacy regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dont Be a Tattle-Tale: Preventing Leakages through Data Dependencies on Access Control Protected Data</title>
      <link>/publication/tattle-tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/tattle-tale/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 
Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@tobiastu?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;&gt;Tobias Tullius&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/black-and-white-rectangular-frame-4dKy7d3lkKM?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;
   --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>/members/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/members/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/admin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
