<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Steve Willoughby | DIPr Lab at PSU</title>
    <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/steve-willoughby/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://diprlab.github.io/author/steve-willoughby/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Steve Willoughby</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://diprlab.github.io/author/steve-willoughby/avatar_hu_6296aa5e920ce26b.png</url>
      <title>Steve Willoughby</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/steve-willoughby/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2025 Week 8</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Title
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Highly Efficient and Scalable Access Control Mechanism for IoT Devices in Pervasive Environments
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Authors
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Alian Yu, Jian Kang, Wei Jiang and Dan Lin
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Abstract
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      With the continuous advancement of sensing, networking, controlling, and computing technologies, there is a growing number of IoT (Internet of Things) devices emerging that are expected to integrate into public infrastructure in the near future. However, the deployment of these smart devices in public venues presents new challenges for existing access control mechanisms, particularly in terms of efficiency. To address these challenges, we have developed a highly efficient and scalable access control mechanism that enables automatic and fine-grained access control management while incurring low overhead in large-scale settings. Our mechanism includes a dual-hierarchy access control structure and associated information retrieval algorithms, which we have used to develop a large-scale IoT device access control system called FACT+. FACT+ overcomes the efficiency issues of granting and inquiring access control status over millions of devices in pervasive environments. Additionally, our system offers a pay-and-consume scheme and plug-and-play device management for convenient adoption by service providers. We have conducted extensive experiments to demonstrate the practicality, effectiveness, and efficiency of our access control mechanism.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Securing IoT Communication Protocols at Scale</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/project/pubsubcontrol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/project/pubsubcontrol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The world of the connected “Internet of Things” is expanding to include more devices which observe our daily lives, routines, locations, and even our state of health. But have the underlying protocols by which they communicate this data kept pace with the need to protect our privacy and security?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we will investigate various “middleware” approaches to injecting dynamic access control agents into existing MQTT broker servers and measure their performance on real and/or simulated network environments as well as their resilience to security threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek to strengthen the protocols underlying the communication between IoT devices, such as MQTT, to adjudicate who is authorized to access which information, where the access parameters may rapidly and frequently change, without impacting performance, based on the implications of the MQTT message topic hierarchical structure combined with geospacial security policy “zones” and techniques to simplfy and consolidate policy rules in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
