<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anadi Shakya | DIPr Lab at PSU</title>
    <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/anadi-shakya/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://diprlab.github.io/author/anadi-shakya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Anadi Shakya</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://diprlab.github.io/author/anadi-shakya/avatar_hu_d7d4ea540fdde860.png</url>
      <title>Anadi Shakya</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/anadi-shakya/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer 2025 Week 2</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/summer/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/summer/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Title
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      An Elephant Under the Microscope: Analyzing the Interaction of Optimizer Components in PostgreSQL
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Authors
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Rico Bergmann, Claudio Hartmann, Dirk Habich, Wolfgang Lehner
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Abstract
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Despite an ever-growing corpus of novel query optimization strategies, the interaction of the core components of query optimizers is still not well understood. This situation can be problematic for two main reasons: On the one hand, this may cause surprising results when two components influence each other in an unexpected way. On the other hand, this can lead to wasted effort in regard to both engineering and research, e.g., when an improvement for one component is dwarfed or entirely canceled out by problems of another component. Therefore, we argue that making improvements to a single optimization component requires a thorough understanding of how these changes might affect the other components. To achieve this understanding, we present results of a comprehensive experimental analysis of the interplay in the traditional optimizer architecture using the widely-used PostgreSQL system as prime representative. Our evaluation and analysis revisit the core building blocks of such an optimizer, i.e. per-column statistics, cardinality estimation, cost model, and plan generation. In particular, we analyze how these building blocks influence each other and how they react when faced with faulty input, such as imprecise cardinality estimates. Based on our results, we draw novel conclusions and make recommendations on how these should be taken into account.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2025 Week 6</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Title
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Grouping, Subsumption, and Disjunctive Join Optimizations in Oracle
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Authors
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Rafi Ahmed, Krishna Kantikiran Pasupuleti, Sriram Tirupattur, Lei Sheng, Hong Su, Mohamed Ziauddin
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Abstract
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Query optimization must evolve with new workloads. As analytic and data warehouse workloads become more ubiquitous, optimization techniques that reduce the amount of data processed during query execution, enable shared computation and avoid expensive data access and joins must be rigorously explored. In this paper, we present aggregate-decomposition techniques as enhancements to an existing query transformation that performs grouping before joins. Consequently, the transformation generates more query rewrite candidates and can also be applied to a larger set of queries. Further, we introduce two new query transformations, i) subsumption of views and subqueries that explores opportunities for sharing computation and ii) union-all duplicator transformation for queries with disjunctive join predicates that removes the need for multiple data access and joins. These techniques are applicable to commonly noticed query patterns in customer workloads and provide significant performance benefit as indicated in our performance study. They have been implemented in Oracle RDBMS.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sieve</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/project/sieve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/project/sieve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SIEVE is a versatile middleware that enhances access control in DBMS, enabling efficient query processing even with a large number of access control policies. We&amp;rsquo;re currently integrating caching to further improve query performance. Additionally, we&amp;rsquo;ve developed a workload generator that simulates various scenarios to test policy models and ensure access control compliance, reflecting real-world conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
