<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Orobosa Ekhator | DIPr Lab at PSU</title>
    <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/orobosa-ekhator/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://diprlab.github.io/author/orobosa-ekhator/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Orobosa Ekhator</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://diprlab.github.io/author/orobosa-ekhator/avatar_hu_4d2e92dc2b0d25db.jpg</url>
      <title>Orobosa Ekhator</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/author/orobosa-ekhator/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer 2025 Week 4</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/summer/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/summer/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Title
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      TSB-UAD: An End-to-End Benchmark Suite for Univariate Time-Series Anomaly Detection
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Authors
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      John Paparrizos ,Yuhao Kang , Paul Boniol , Ruey S. Tsay ,Themis Palpanas , Michael J. Franklin
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Abstract
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      The detection of anomalies in time series has gained ample academic and industrial attention. However, no comprehensive benchmark exists to evaluate time-series anomaly detection methods. It is common to use (i) proprietary or synthetic data, often biased to support particular claims; or (ii) a limited collection of publicly available datasets. Consequently, we often observe methods performing exceptionally well in one dataset but surprisingly poorly in another, creating an illusion of progress. To address the issues above, we thoroughly studied over one hundred papers to identify, collect, process, and systematically format datasets proposed in the past decades. We summarize our eort in TSB-UAD, a new benchmark to ease the evaluation of univariate time-series anomaly detection methods. Overall, TSB-UAD contains 13766 time series with labeled anomalies spanning dierent domains with high variability of anomaly types, ratios, and sizes. TSB-UAD includes 18 previously proposed datasets containing 1980 time series and we contribute two collections of datasets. Specically, we generate 958 time series using a principled methodology for transforming 126 time-series classication datasets into time series with labeled anomalies. In addition, we present data transformations with which we introduce new anomalies, resulting in 10828 time series with varying complexity for anomaly detection. Finally, we evaluate 12 representative methods demonstrating that TSB-UAD is a robust resource for assessing anomaly detection methods. We make our data and code available at www.timeseries.org/TSB-UAD. TSB-UAD provides a valuable, reproducible, and frequently updated resource to establish a leaderboard of univariate time-series anomaly detection methods.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2025 Week 9</title>
      <link>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://diprlab.github.io/dbrg/events/2025/spring/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Title
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      In-Database Time Series Clustering
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Authors
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Yunxiang Su, Kenny Ye Liang, Shaoxu Song
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
      Abstract
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Time series data are often clustered repeatedly across various time ranges to mine frequent subsequence patterns from different periods, which could further support downstream applications. Existing state-of-the-art (SOTA) time series clustering method, such as K-Shape, can proficiently cluster time series data referring to their shapes. However, in-database time series clustering problem has been neglected, especially in IoT scenarios with large-volume data and high efficiency demands. Most time series databases employ LSM-Tree based storage to support intensive writings, yet causing underlying data points out-of-order in timestamps. Therefore, to apply existing out-of-database methods, all data points must be fully loaded into memory and chronologically sorted. Additionally, out-of-database methods must cluster from scratch each time, making them inefficient when handling queries across different time ranges. In this work, we propose an in-database adaptation of SOTA time series clustering method K-Shape. Moreover, to solve the problem that K-Shape cannot efficiently handle long time series, we propose Medoid-Shape, as well as its in-database adaptation for further acceleration. Extensive experiments are conducted to demonstrate the higher efficiency of our proposals, with comparable effectiveness. Remarkably, all proposals have already been implemented in an open-source commodity time series database, Apache IoTDB.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
